Finding Aid for Harry Burns Hutchins papers
Bentley Historical Library
Harry Burns Hutchins papers
1879-1930
Bentley Historical Library
Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930
851733 Aa 2; AC; UAM
22 linear feet
Professor of law and president of the University of Michigan. Papers include correspondence, reports, and speeches relating to all aspects of his University activities; and visual materials.
The Hutchins papers were transferred to the library from the University of Michigan Business Office. (Donor no. 73 .)
The collection is open for research.
Harry Burns Hutchins was born near Lisbon, New Hampshire, on April 8,1847 and received his preparatory education in the east. However, from the time he entered the University of Michigan as an undergraduate, his life and work were closely tied to Michigan. As a student, Hutchins was a member of the Alpha Delta Phi fraternity and an editor of the University Chronicle. He was the first student to receive a degree from James B. Angell in 1871, and upon graduation worked for a year as superintendent of the Owosso schools. Hutchins returned to the university as an instructor in rhetoric and history and became an assistant professor a year later. During the three years he held that post, he studied law and began practicing law in Mount Clemens in 1876.
On December 27, 1872, Harry B. Hutchins married Marry Louise Crocker, of Birmingham, Michigan. Mary was born on January 14, 1857, the daughter of Fandira Emery Crocker and Thomas Martin Crocker. She was a descendent of Thomas Hooker, founder of Hartford, Connecticut, and Deacon William Crocker, one of the early settlers of Cape Cod, Massachusetts. Mrs. Hutchins graduated from Mt. Clemens High School in 1869.
In 1884, Mr. Hutchins returned to the University of Michigan as Jay Professor of Law. His teaching and organizational skills were recognized by Cornell University which invited him to organize its law school in 1887. He later returned to Ann Arbor and was appointed dean of the University of Michigan's Department of Law in 1895. He served as interim president of the university in 1897-98 while President Angell was serving as envoy to Turkey, and again in 1909-10 after Angell's resignation. In spite of Hutchins reluctance to accept the appointment as president at age 63, the Regents prevailed upon him, and he agreed to serve for five years. Letters of July 5, 1910, to Regents Leland and Knappen (box 2, folder 1) detail the conditions of his acceptance; numerous letters in the next few months replying to congratulatory messages he received, reiterate his doubts and hesitation. However, once in office he applied himself to the job with diligence. Hutchins believed that the university should be a leader and a contributor to the public good. Toward that end, he travelled extensively in his first year in office lecturing and meeting with alumni to encourage their support of the university by establishing active regional alumni organizations. He also oversaw the beginnings of an extension service to better serve the people of the Michigan. At first only a kind of speakers' bureau, which arranged for university professors to lecture to various groups outstate, it later added courses in outlying localities for which university credit could be earned.
President Hutchins took a personal interest in students, often inviting them to call on him, but he was also a strict disciplinarian who held students to a high standard of academic work and personal morality. His term in office was extended beyond five years by the demands of World War I, and he served until 1920.
Mr. and Mrs. Hutchins hosted many friends and distinguished guests, including U.S. President William H. Taft, to their home in Ann Arbor and their summer cottage in Cotuit, Massachusetts. Mary Hutchins was a member of many organizations including the Daughters of the American Revolution, a Regent of the Sarah Caswell Angell Chapter, the National Committee for the American flag, the Michigan Chapter of Colonial Dames, the American Association of University Women (Ann Arbor branch), the Faculty Women's Club, and a founding member of the Ann Arbor Women's Club. Mary Hutchins died of a heart attack on August 2, 1927.
After his retirement in 1920, Hutchins became President Emeritus and continued to serve the university in various capacities until his death. Harry B. Hutchins died on January 25, 1930.
The Harry B. Hutchins papers cover the years 1879 through 1929, and include records generated during his years as professor and dean of the law department, President of the University of Michigan, and in retirement. Boxes 1-18 are primarily comprised of correspondence. Reports of the departments, schools, and other units of the university are contained in box 19, folders 30-32, and box 20, folders 1-13. As president, Hutchins did not regularly submit annual reports to the Board of Regents. Additional materials include speeches, photographs, and biographical material.
Afro-Americans -- Michigan.; Conservation of natural resources -- Michigan.; Elections -- Michigan -- 1912.; Elections -- Michigan -- 1914.; United States -- Emigration and immigration.; Hillsdale (Mich.); Indians of North America -- Michigan.; Jews -- Michigan.; Philippines -- History -- 1898-1946.; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1912.; Prohibition -- Michigan.; Radicalism -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Temperance -- Michigan.; Women -- Suffrage -- United States.; Spanish-American War, 1898.; Greek letter societies -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Students, Foreign -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Hazing -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Education and the war.; World War, 1914-1918 -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Immigrants -- United States.; Ann Arbor (Mich.) -- Dwellings.; Ann Arbor (Mich.) -- Streets.; Camp Davis (University of Michigan); Drawings.; Dwellings -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Dwellings -- New Hampshire.; Monroe Street (Ann Arbor, Mich.); New Hampshire -- Dwellings.; Photographs.; Prints.; Streets -- Michigan -- Ann Arbor.; Photographs.; Women's resources -- biographical information in finding aid.; American Peace Congress (4th: 1913: St. Louis); B'nai B'rith Hillel Foundation (University of Michigan); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940.; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Intercollegiate Conference of Faculty Representatives.; Ku Klux Klan (1915-); United States. Army. Reserve Officers' Training Corps.; University of Michigan -- Buildings.; University of Michigan. Chinese Students Club.; University of Michigan. Department of Astronomy.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Classical Studies.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Military Science and Tactics.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physics.; University of Michigan -- Faculty.; University of Michigan -- Football.; University of Michigan -- Students.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Societies, etc.; University of Michigan -- Law School.; University of Michigan. Library.; Michigan Union.; University of Michigan. University Museum.; University of Michigan. President.; University of Michigan. School of Music.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Social life and customs -- 1911-1920.; University of Michigan -- Students -- Conduct of life.; Hutchins, Harry B. (Harry Burns), 1847-1930.; Hutchins family.; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-1971.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan -- Faculty.; University of Michigan -- Law School.; University of Michigan. President.; Shaw, Wilfred Byron, 1881-1959.; Adams, Charles Kendall, 1835-1902.; Adams, Henry Carter, 1851-1921.; American Neutral Conference Committee.; American Protective Tariff League.; American Union Against Militarism.; Angell, Alexis C. (Alexis Caswell), 1857-1932.; Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Angell, James Rowland, 1869-1949.; Anti-Saloon League of Michigan.; Babst, Earl D., 1870-1967.; Barbour, Levi L. (Levi Lewis), 1840-1925.; Bartelme, Philip George, 1876-1954.; Bates, Henry Moore, 1869-1949.; Beakes, Samuel Willard, 1861-1927.; Beal, Junius E. (Junius Emery), 1860-1942.; Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.; Boudeman, Dallas.; Bowers, Claude Gernade, 1879-1958.; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925.; Bulkley, Harry C. (Harry Conant), 1870-; Burrows, Julius C. (Julius Caesar), 1837-1915.; Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Butler, Nicholas Murray, 1862-1947.; Cabot, Hugh, 1872-1945.; Chapin, Roy D. (Roy Dikeman), 1880-1936.; Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934.; Comstock, William Alfred, 1877-1949.; Cook, William W. (William Wilson), 1858-1930.; Cooley, Charles Horton, 1864-1929.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Copeland, Royal S. (Royal Samuel), 1868-1938.; Cramton, Louis C. (Louis Convers), 1875-; Daniels, Josephus, 1862-1948.; Demmon, Isaac Newton, 1842-1920.; D'Ooge, Martin Luther, 1839-1915.; Douglas, Lloyd C. (Lloyd Cassel), 1877-1951.; Dow, Earle Wilbur, 1868-1946.; Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963.; Effinger, John R. (John Robert), 1869-1933.; Eggert, Carl Edgar, 1868-1944.; Ferris, Woodbridge N., 1853-1928.; Fletcher, Frank Ward, 1853-1922.; Gore, Victor Michael, 1858-1941.; Grant, Claudius Buchanan, 1835-1921.; Grant, John Henry, 1857-1913.; Groesbeck, Alexander J. (Alexander Joseph), 1873-1953.; Hanchett, Benjamin Sawtell, 1868-1933.; Hart, Albert Bushnell, 1854-1943.; Hinsdale, W. B. (Wilbert B.), 1851-1944.; Hobbs, William Herbert, 1864-1952.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Hubbard, Lucius L. (Lucius Lee), 1849-1933.; Hudson, Joseph Lowthian, 1846-1912.; Hudson, Richard, 1845-1915.; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948.; Hussey, Ethel Fountain, 1865-1915.; Hussey, William Joseph, 1862-1926.; Illinois Vigilance Association.; Johnson, Elias Finley, 1861-1933.; Jordan, Myra Beach, 1863-1946.; Keeler, Fred L.; Kellogg, John Harvey, 1852-1943.; Kelsey, Francis W. (Francis Willey), 1858-; Knappen, Loyal Edwin, 1854-1930.; Koch, Theodore Wesley, 1871-1941.; Labadie, Jo, 1850-1933.; Lansing, Robert, 1864-1928.; League to Enforce Peace.; Leland, Frank Bruce.; Little, Clarence C. (Clarence Cook), 1888-; McLaughlin, Andrew Cunningham, 1861-1947.; Malcolm, George A. (George Arthur), 1881-1961.; Mapes, Carl Edgar, 1874-1939.; Mayo, William James, 1861-1939.; Men's League for Woman Suffrage of the State of Michigan.; Mott, John Raleigh, 1865-1955.; Murfin, James Orin, 1875-1940.; National Child Labor Committee (U.S.); National Conference on Race Betterment.; National Conservation Congress. n 5th, Washington, D.C., 1913.; National Home Finding Society for Colored Children.; National Peace Federation.; National Religious Training School.; National Urban League.; Newberry, Truman Handy, 1864-1945.; Osborn, Chase S. (Chase Salmon), 1860-; Page, Walter Hines, 1855-1918.; Michigan State Grange.; Pillsbury, W. B. (Walter Bowers), 1872-1960.; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946.; Pingree, Hazen S., 1840-1901.; Quezon, Manuel Luis, 1878-1944.; Reeves, Jesse Siddall, 1872-1942.; Reighard, Jacob Ellsworth, 1861-1942.; Riggs, Henry Earle, 1865-1949.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937.; Ruthven, Alexander Grant, 1882-1971.; Sawyer, Walter H. (Walter Hulme), 1861-1931.; Schurman, Jacob Gould, 1854-1942.; Sleeper, Albert E., 1862-1934.; Smith, Shirley Wheeler, 1875-1959.; Smith, William Alden, 1859-1932.; Stimson, Henry L. (Henry Lewis), 1867-1950.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.; Townsend, Charles E. (Charles Elroy), 1856-1924.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Van Tyne, Claude Halstead, 1869-1930.; Vaughan, Victor C. (Victor Clarence), 1851-1929.; Ward, Marcus Llewellyn, 1875-1963.; Warner, Frederick Maltby, 1865-1923.; Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915.; Wedemeyer, William Walter, 1873-1913.; Wenley, R. M. (Robert Mark), 1861-1929.; Wheeler, Burton K. (Burton Kendall), 1882-1975.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924.; Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927.; World Court League.; World Peace Foundation.; Wright, Luther Lamphere, 1856-1922.; Hutchins, Mary Louise Crocker, 1857-1927.
- Correspondence and other Papers, 1879-1930; 18.5 linear feet
  The correspondence is arranged in strict chronological order according to the date of the letter received and the date of the reply to it. This means that the letter and its response are sometimes widely separated. However, the date of the reply was often noted on the incoming letter in blue pencil. Two indexes have been created to provide some access points to the chronological correspondence files.
  A name index lists many of the most significant authors or recipients of letters. The alphabetical listing cites letters by the author by date. A second index provides access by broad topics and subjects. In the index notations, dates for original letters and responses are given. If the reply is in the same folder as the incoming letter, the dates in the index appear in order, separated by a comma. If the reply is in another folder, its notation is preceded by an R and the box, folder number, and date are given. Starting in 1913, copies of replies are sometimes on the back of the incoming letter itself so the researcher should check there also
  President Hutchins continued the operation of the university as it had been under previous presidents, although with increasing expansion of course offerings and student numbers university management was beginning to become unwieldy. There was no organizational structure demarking administrative functions. This lack meant that a wide range of inquiries were addressed to the president -- including those regarding appointments, admissions, student financial aid, and medical care in the university hospitals. These were referred to the heads of the various departments and schools, to the secretary of the university, who oversaw financial affairs, or to the Student Christian Association, which arranged for student jobs.
  An indication of how highly regarded the university was across the country may be found in the large number of inquiries from university or government officials in recently admitted states in the west where state systems of higher education were being developed. The range of topics on which they sought advice may be seen in the index listings under "Inquiries from other Educational Institutions".
  - "Letters Written by Men of Note which are to be found in the Hutchins Papers", undated (Box 1)
  - 1879-June 30, 1910, 43 folders (Box 1)
  - July 1, 1910-May 7, 1911, 42 folders (Box 2)
  - May 8, 1911-December 31, 1911, 28 folders (Box 3)
  - January 1, 1912-June 30, 1912, 24 folders (Box 4)
  - July 1, 1912-March 31, 1913, 36 folders (Box 5)
  - April 1, 1913-December 31, 1913, 30 folders (Box 6)
  - January 1, 1914-June 30, 1914, 24 folders (Box 7)
  - July 1, 1914-December 31, 1914, 24 folders (Box 8)
  - January 1, 1915-June 30, 1915, 24 folders (Box 9)
  - July 1, 1915-December 31, 1915, 25 folders (Box 10)
  - January 1 1916-August 31, 1916, 31 folders (Box 11)
  - September 1, 1916-March 31, 1917, 28 folders (Box 12)
  - April 1, 1917-September 30, 1917, 24 folders (Box 13)
  - October 1, 1917-March 31, 1918, 24 folders (Box 14)
  - April 1, 1918-August 31, 1918, 20 folders (Box 15)
  - September 1, 1918-Jan 27, 1919; 22 folders (Box 16)
  - February 1, 1919-August 31, 1919, 28 folders (Box 17)
  - September 1, 1919-March, 31, 1920; 32 folders (Box 18)
  - April 1, 1920-1930, 25 folders (Box 19)
    (folder undated 1920 includes Committee of Instructor's Plea for Salary Increase)
- Biographical Material
  The Biographical Materials series consist of a typescript biography of Hutchins written by Harry C. Hutchins, Hutchins' will and an obituary of Mary Hutchins.
  - Biography of Harry B. Hutchins, typescript by Harry C. Hutchins (Box 19)
    (also includes will of HBH and an obituary of Mary Hutchins)
- Speeches and Articles
  Several commencement and baccalaureate addresses, presentations to the American Political Science Association, and talks and articles on the university and academic affairs comprise the Speeches and Articles series.
  - Speeches, 3 folders (Box 19)
- Reports of Colleges, Schools and Departments
  The Reports of Colleges, Schools and Departments series includes reports from deans and heads of department. IN some cases these are annual or five year reports. A number are reports specifically requested by Hutchins in 1920 to document developments during his administration.
  - College of L.S.&A., 1919; 1920 (Box 19)
  - College of Pharmacy, 1915; 1920 (Box 19)
  - Dean of Women, 1920 (Box 19)
    (Includes information on the development of women's dormitories (such as the Women's League), the increase in female attendance, benefits of self-governance, and impact of WWI on academic curriculum. Witten by second Dean of Women, Myra Beach Jordan (1920-1922), and covers the time period 1909-1920.)
  - Department Of Engineering, 1910 (Box 19)
  - Extension Service, 1915; 1920 (Box 20)
  - Graduate School, 1910; 1914-1915; 1920 (Box 20)
  - Health Service, 1916 (Box 20)
  - Homeopathic School, 1910; 1915; 1920 (Box 20)
  - Law School, 1915; 1921 (Box 20)
  - Library, 1920 (Box 20)
  - Medical School, 1910; 1915; 1920 (Box 20)
  - Observatory, 1915 (Box 20)
  - School of Dentistry, 1910; 1915; 1920 (Box 20)
  - Summer Session, 1910; 1911; 1920 (Box 20)
  - University Hospital, 1915; 1920 (Box 20)
- Miscellaneous Papers
  The Miscellaneous Papers series consists of correspondence and other material arranged by topic. There are files relating to alumni affairs-largely arrangements for Hutchins' speaking engagements at regional alumni associations, commencement activities and awarding of honorary degrees, convocations, his participation in the affairs of the Carnegie Foundation, and files concerning the University's participation in World War I, including campus ROTC and military training camps for students.
  - Alumni Association and commencement
    - General, 3 folders (Box 20)
    - Alumni Clubs (Box 20)
    - Buffalo Alumni Association, 1916 (Box 20)
    - Chicago Alumni Association, 1915 (Box 20)
    - Chicago Alumni Association, 1916 (Box 20)
    - Cleveland Alumni Association, 1915 (Box 20)
    - Cleveland and Philadelphia Alumni Association, 1916 (Box 20)
    - Columbus (OH), 1914 (Box 20)
    - Kansas City, St. Louis and Springfield (IL) Alumni Associations, 1914 (Box 20)
    - Kansas city and Oklahoma City, 1916 (Box 20)
    - Milwaukee Alumni Meeting, 1920 (Box 20)
    - Minneapolis and Northwestern Alumni Associations, 1915 (Box 20)
    - New England Alumni Association, 1916 (Box 20)
    - New York City, Rochester, Washington, Buffalo, 1914 (Box 20)
    - New York and Washington D.C., 1915 (Box 20)
    - New York City and Washington D.C., 1916 (Box 20)
    - Philadelphia Alumni Association (Box 20)
    - Rochester District Alumni Association, 1914 (Box 20)
  - Carnegie Foundation, 1910-1920; 15 folders (Box 20)
  - Letters of congratulations on appointment as president, 1910; 3 folders (Box 20)
  - Commencement, 1911-1920
    - 1911-1916, 7 folders (Box 20)
    - 1917-1920, 4 folders (Box 21)
  - Convocations, 1913-1920; 4 folders (Box 21)
  - Honorary Degrees, 1911-1920; 11 folders (Box 21)
  - Non-resident Lecturers, 1911-1920; 6 folders (Box 21)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence
    - Affiliation between University and Normal School, undated (Box 22)
    - American Council on Education, 1919-1920 (Box 22)
    - Forestry School, 1908-1917 (Box 22)
    - Henry Strong Educational Fund, 1912 (Box 22)
    - Newlands Bill, 1916-1917 (Box 22)
  - National Dinner, 1911 (Box 22)
  - Selective Subject Card Catalog to the Harry Burns Hutchins papers, undated (Box 22)
  - The University in World War I, ROTC and Training Camps for Students, 1913-1918; 14 folders (Box 22)
  - Student Notebooks on course in geometry, U of M, 1871; 2 volumes (Box 22)
- Visual Material
  Visual materials include photographic and print portraits, including drawing by Wilfred Shaw; photographs of Hutchins lecturing, with faculty and students at Camp Davis, with family, and with successor, Alexander Ruthven; also prints depicting Hutchins, and Hutchins' homes in New Hampshire and in Ann Arbor, Michigan.
  - Photographs
    - Henry B. Hutchins Portraits, 2 folders (Box 22)
    - Family and group photos, 2 folders (Box 22)
  - Prints (Box 22)
    (mostly portraits of Hutchins from publications)
Selective Subject Index to Correspondence
This index covers only materials generated during President Hutchins term as interim president, 1909-1910, and as president, 1910-1920. Papers of 1897-98, when he was acting president, are not included in the index. The correspondence of that year deals mainly with routine business matters -- requests for catalogs, inquiries about entrance requirements, or lecture arrangements for the president, and letters of recommendation. A few letters touch on such matters of public interest as state support of higher education, or the university's position on the Cuban question and the war with Spain.
The subject index has been organized into five broad categories: Administration, Building Program, Academic Units and Programs, Student Life and Campus Social Problems, Social and Political Issues of the Time. Index entries under subject terms include name of correspondent, box and folder numbers, and date of the document.
Since the university affairs were centralized in the president's office, the bulk of the correspondence falls under the heading of Administration (Sec. I). Although Hill Auditorium and the power plant were being completed when he took office and plans were being made for a natural sciences building and women's residence halls, in general there was a minimal amount of new building on campus during Hutchins's tenure (Sec. II). Few changes were made in academic units or the work of the departments in this time. Thus, the relatively small amount of correspondence related to academic affairs is contained in Sec. III, but most such materials will be found in the papers of departmental heads and deans.
I. Administration
General
Christian Science Monitor 10-22, 12/10 & 12/13/15
Hogan, 3-5, 7/16 & 7/19/12
McQuade, 5-1, 7/5/12, R5-2, 7/8/12
Admissions policies
Butler (Columbia), 3-25, 12/1/11, copies of same letter re: centralization of admissions were sent on same date to presidents of Yale, Wisconsin, Cornell, Harvard, Universities of Illinois & Minnesota, and Ohio State. No incoming replies were found in files.
Admissions requirements
4-6, 2/16/12, 22 replies from superintendents of schools to letter sent by HBH re: suitability of proposed entrance requirements.
Drouyer, 4-24, 6/24/12
Sawdon, 4-19, 5/19 & 5/20/12
Vincent, 3-25, 12/1/11
Warriner, 4-9, 4/7/12; 4-10, 3/14/12
Adviser system
Effinger, 5-8, 8/24/12
Hayes, 5-16, 10/22/12
Alumni organization and activities
General
Angell, 1-26, 2/12/10
Chapaton, 2-6, 10/19/10
Copeland, 5-29, 2/7/13
Lenderink, 8-12, 10/28 & 10/31/14
Lessing, 1-19, 10/31/09; 1-21, 11/24/09
McReynolds, 2-5, 10/8/10, R10/14/10 Throughout 1909, 1910, & 1911 there are numerous letters regarding arrangements for President Hutchins to speak at alumni meetings nationwide.
Oxtoby, 6-22, 10/25/13
Seaman, 9-24, 6/28/15
U-M National dinner held in New York City
Babst, 2-24, 2/13/11, R2-25, 2/20/11; 2-26, 2/27/11; 2-27, 3/3/11, R2-28, 3/9/11
Kern, 2-20, 1/27/11
Maclay-Sunderland, 4-4, 1/25/12
O'Brien, 2-19, 1/17/11
In folders 2-19 and 2-20, in addition to the Kern and O'Brien letters, there are many others pertaining to the arrangements for the national alumni dinner held in February 1911.
Athletics
General
Graves, 6-22, 10/31/13, R6-23, 11/3/13
Control of athletics
Bartelme, 5-22, 12/11 & 12/12/12
Effinger, 5-22, 12/14/12
Thomas, 3-23, 11/25/11, R3-24, 11/27/11; 3-25, 12/1/11
Rose Bowl invitation
Baer, 10-16, 10/28/15; 10-19, 11/17/15
Bartelme, 10-17, 11/8/15
Bulkley, 10-16, 10/27/15, R10-17,11/4/15; 11/8/15